oh boy welcome to unit 4 this unit
covers the time period 1800 to 1848 in
American history I would give an
overview of what that entails but I
believe that's the videoos job to do
this unit is worth quite a bit on your
AP exam though so no skipping it as for
this video this video is simply equipped
together video of all my unit 4 topic
review videos without the AP style
questions at the end of each video if
you want to try your hand at some AP
style questions associated with each
topic of unit 4 the unit 4 playlist is
in the description to support more
content like this please consider
checking out my socials but anyway let's
get into to unit
4 topic 4.2 is about the age of
Jefferson's term in office and really
what just happened so Thomas Jefferson a
DieHard Democratic Republican takes
office after the Federalist rule of
Adams continuing into this period we
have these two parties debating over
relations with the French and the
British and powers of the federal
government all things covered in my
topic 3.10 video but we start seeing
debates over something new around this
period known as tariffs which is a tax
on imported goods meaning Goods coming
into America this tax is paid by
American companies which typically raise
their prices to accommodate for the tax
understand that in a world where the
south is typically known as a rural
agrarian expanse known for farming and
the north is known for their Industries
and manufacturers the South would be
negatively affected by these tariffs as
they need to import lots of goods
because of the lack of Industries they
have the north would benefit from this
tax As Americans would start only buying
American manufactured goods the
Democratic Republicans hated the idea of
tariffs aligning themselves with the
South the federal list liked the ideas
of tariffs aligning themselves with a
northern view during Jefferson's
presidency he enacted the trade embargo
of 1807 which made it so America would
stop importing Britain's Goods this
would end up backfiring and hurting the
American economy but possibly the most
famous part of Jefferson's presidency
was the case Marbury V Madison which was
a Supreme Court case that established
the concept of judicial review which
allowed the Supreme Court to review and
invalidate actions taken by the other
branches of government if they are
deemed unconstitutional and another
popular thing is even more Westward
Expansion the US wanted the land of New
Orleans and negotiated with France to
get it France offered the entire
Louisiana territory as they were facing
Financial issues because of Napoleon and
the US bought it for $15 million now
with all this territory the US wanted to
map it so they sent Lewis and Clark on
an expedition with the Native American
guide of saaka to help them they went
all the way from St Louis to the Pacific
and mapped out the western territories
and realized truly how big it was topic
4.3 starts talking about tensions in the
US economy and differing viewpoints some
war broke out between Britain and the US
in 1812 caused by British supporting
Native American tribes and impressment
on American Sailors it ended in a draw
with the Treaty of G that the US saws a
win mostly because of the nationalism
caused by the Battle of New Orleans
during this war Federalists met at the
Hartford Convention discussing
disapproval of the war in potential
secession after America quote unquote
won this war this convention would lead
to the party's demise and that leads
into the introduction of a man who lots
of people don't like including me Henry
Clay this guy was a lawyer Secretary of
State leader of a future political party
and so influential in this period he
introduced something known as the
American system this was a response to
the War of 1812 and suggested to provide
National Economic growth by establishing
a protective tariff creating a national
bank and funding internal improvements
like roads and canals this was so
controversial and caused many debates to
arise from the Democratic Republicans
later known as the Democrats who opposed
it and the new National Republicans
later known as the wigs who supported it
the Supreme Court had its say with its
molok V Maryland case which established
that Federal power Trump state power but
who cares about that it's time to talk
about early Civil War causes so
throughout the Early Republic States
kept getting added and became either a
slave or free state as this continued in
1819 there was a bounce of 11 slave
states and 11 free states but as America
was expanding Westward Missouri was
added as a state the South wanted it to
be a slave state and it ended up
becoming one the north however felt
cheated and made the Missouri Compromise
which added Maine as an official free
state and said above a certain line
there couldn't be any more slave states
this shows the start of weak compromises
creating tension upon tension until
eventual war and how about even more
Civil War causes the protective Tariff
of 1828 put attacks on imported goods
and the South was very mad at it even to
the point they called it the Tariff of
Obama ations this led to the South
Carolina exposition and the
Nullification Crisis where the South
openly protested the Tariff there likely
would have been War if it wasn't for
khone and Clay who proposed the Tariff
of 1833 which would lower the tax over
the years but what this shows is the
South can and will Revolt if it doesn't
like something foreshadowing the
eventual Civil War topic 4.4 is about
America's relations with other countries
throughout the beginning of the 19th
century so it's fair to say America was
struggling in this time to create a
global presence turns out inciting a
revolution to create a nation doesn't
get respect from other nations that that
have been on the globe for much longer
the US tried to rectify this through
things like the War of 1812 but they
needed more land what they did first was
acquire Florida from Spain in 1819 under
these two treaties and they also started
a war where they forced the seminal
tribes out of the Forida lands the US
also decided to prove their Naval might
which they did by inciting the Barberry
Wars against North African States but
the big thing to talk about is as
America kept spreading Westward there
was more and more conflict with Native
Americans Britain saw this as an
opportunity to support the Native
Americans against the Americans this
would cause President James Monroe to
pass the Monroe Doctrine which declared
to Britain that any involvement in
America by European powers would be seen
as an act of war and to add insult to
injury America also passed mayon's bill
number two which prohibited French and
British warships from entering American
Harbors topic 4.5 introduces the market
Revolution the time of which great
Innovation and mechanization Agriculture
and commerce occurred is largely called
and known as the market Revolution which
is just a little part of the larger
industrial revolution of the world
inventions like the textile machiner
steam engines interchangeable parts the
Telegraph and agricultural inventions
made production methods of different
products so much faster and easier
causing entrepreneurs to make a lot of
goods and businesses causing people to
buy more goods and you get the idea one
thing to note about the market
Revolution is the difference in
evolution between the North and the
South the North became a place for all
Industries housing all types of
manufacturing and businesses the Advent
of the Cott engin caused the South to
farm cotton furiously making the South
grow up making mostly Farms having
slaves work at them and selling the
cotton from those farms for massive
amounts of money now of course the South
needed to sell these Goods to other
countries mostly but different
legislation and Judicial Systems Support
of development of roads and canals and
railroads caused American Regional
markets and selling to grow this would
link the North and the South heavily but
it should still be noted that no matter
how much the north and south are
connected in this time period before the
Civil War these areas were different on
values and culture and could not coexist
peacefully with one another the market
Revolution would also have a massive
impact on society and culture as well
but that is a next video toic 4.6
introduces the societal and cultural
impacts of the market Revolution the
Innovations in technology Agriculture
and commerce we talked about last time
didn't just make goods and businesses
they changed how people lived worked and
thought about themselves large numbers
of international migrants flooded into
industrializing Northern cities to find
factory work an example of a city
growing heavily industrialized from this
being Philadelphia at the same time a
lot of Americans moved west of the appol
building new communities along the Ohio
and Mississippi rivers with some cities
growing here like St Louis and
Cincinnati this movement created a new
dynamic between regions as the north
urbanized while the West focused on
agriculture next let's talk about wealth
in Class Manufacturing growth led to
higher standards of living for some
folks creating a bigger middle class and
a wealthy business Elite but it should
be noted it also created a large and
growing population of laboring poor who
worked for long hours for low wages in
these factories life was better for some
but definitely not for all as for gender
and family roles with the rise of
factories many Americans both men and
women stopped relying on farming to
survive instead they worked to produce
goods for distant markets this shift
brought about new ideas of gender roles
women especially were expected to stay
home and embrace domestic ideals which
emphasize the separation of Public Work
life for men and private home life for
women not everybody was happy about this
topic 4.7 talks about expanding
democracy from 1800 to 1848 Democracy in
America went from being exclusive to
rich landowning white men to slightly
less Exclusive by the 1840s almost all
adult white men could vote so is that
progress kind of the big shift came with
the elimin the property requirements for
voting before this you had to own land
to cast a ballot but as more States
dropped this rule voting rights expanded
and participatory democracy became a
thing one key event you should know is
the door rebellion in Rhode Island where
Thomas door and his supporters pushed
for a new state constitution to expand
voting rights since the original charter
only let landowners vote basically more
people got involved in politics however
it's important to note this only applied
to white men women black Americans and
Indigenous people were still left out
now with more people voting political
parties warned the actual details of
these political parties will be covered
next video but for now all you should
know is that the whole political
framework of the 1820s up to the Civil
War was known as the second party system
oh boy Andrew Jackson we already get to
talk about such an amazing man and
before I get canceled on Twitter I'd
like to say that I'm using a rare
attribute called sarcasm so new
political parties emerged in the 1820s
and 1830s on one side you had the
Democrats led by Andrew Jackson who
believed in a limited federal government
Jackson was all about the Common Man
opposing Elites and big government in
institutions he famously hated the
National Bank calling it a corrupt tool
of the wealthy he vetoed its recharter
In 1832 and moved federal funds to State
Banks known as pet banks on the other
side you had the wigs led by Henry Clay
who supported a stronger federal
government remember that American System
we talked about before well the wigs
loved it the thing is the American
system embodied every single thing
Andrew Jackson despised the debates on
the American system weren't just
political they shaped the economy
infrastructure in the direction of the
country as expansion roared heavily on
the frontier Jackson backed the frontier
settlers with policies like the Indian
Removal Act of 1830 which forced Native
American tribes off of their land this
led to the trail of tiers where
thousands of Cherokee were forcibly
relocated to what is now Oklahoma
suffering greatly along the way
Jackson's policies made him a hero to
many Frontier settlers but his use of
federal power sparked Fierce debates
about whether the government was
protecting citizens or abusing its power
especially when it came to Native lands
in the economy topic 4.9 talks about the
development of a new American culture
between 1800 and 1848 America wasn't
just growing politically or economically
it was developing its own national
identity this new National culture
combined American European and Regional
influences in art you had movements like
the Hudson River School which painted
breathtaking Landscapes of the American
frontier it wasn't just for art sake it
symbolized Manifest Destiny and the idea
that American Natural Beauty was
something special meanwhile writers like
Washington Irving gave us stories like
The Legend of Sleepy Hollow blending
European storytelling Traditions with
American settings and themes but it
wasn't all spooky stories and pretty
paintings philosophy was evolving too
case in point transcendentalism a
movement led by people like Ralph Waldo
Emerson and Henry David tho they
believed in individualism nature and the
idea that humans could Achieve Personal
Perfection sounds inspiring right but it
also had a political Edge
transcendentalists were big on social
reform especially abolitionism and
women's rights on the darker side of
American culture Gothic literature was
making its Mark the big person here is
Edgar Allen Poe with stories like The
Telltale Heart which is literally a
story describing Vivid detail killing an
old man dismembering the body in a
bathtub and stuffing the body parts
under a floorboard I mean hats off to
this man finally architecture played a
key role in shaping the national
identity buildings in Washington DC like
the White House of the capital were
designed with neoclassical architecture
inspired by a Greece and Rome this is
because America wanted to position
itself as a modern Republic with deep
roots and democratic ideals so the
Second Great Awakening what is it short
answer it was a religious revival but
more than that it was a massive cultural
shift that reshaped americ am society
and politics so you might be wondering
what caused the second grade awakening
well a few things first was the rise of
democratic and individualistic beliefs
second was a response to rationalism
because of criticism of the
Enlightenment being too rational based
and let's not forget the market
Revolution which uprooted communities
and made people more mobile creating new
opportunities for religious movements to
spread here's some examples of parts of
this movement camp meetings became huge
social events especially in the frontier
creatures like Charles G fidley LED
emotional Fury revivals in places like
the burned over District of New York
where religious enthusiasm Ran So High
it was said that there was no one left
to convert the Second Great Awakening
also sparked major reform movements
religious leaders preached that
individuals could Achieve Personal
salvation and improve Society this
inspired people to tackle issues like
abolitionism Temperance and women's
rights jeren Lee and Harry hoer hoer
haer we'll go with hoer two prominent
africanamerican preachers challenged
traditional ideas by showing that black
Americans and women could lead in
spiritual life and one more thing new
religious movements emerged Joseph Smith
founded the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints or Mormons while
William Miller's predictions about the
end of the world led to the formation of
the Adventist churches so between 1800
and 1848 America experienced a wave of
reform movements that aimed to fix
society's problems and expand rights and
opportunities first let's talk about
what sparked these movements the second
grade awakening played a huge role it
wasn't just a religious revival it
encouraged people to believe that
individuals could improve themselves and
Society this combined with a market
Revolution and greater Mobility made
people more interested in reforming
moral and social issues so let's look at
some reform movements first up abolition
the Abolitionist Movement grew in the
north calling for the immediate end of
slavery leaders like William Lloyd
Garrison published The Liberator
demanding freedom for enslaved people
meanwhile free African-Americans like
Frederick Douglas became powerful voices
in the movement sharing firsthand
accounts of slavery's then there
was women's rights in 1848 reformers
like Elizabeth Katy Stanton and lria
organized The cica Falls Convention
where they called for the greater
equality of women they even issued the
Declaration of Sentiments which marred
language from the Declaration of
Independence to demand women's rights to
vote this caused this time period to be
dubbed the era of first wave feminism
the temperance movement aimed to reduce
alcohol consumption reformers believed
drinking led to Poverty crime and broken
families and of course you know that
there's no way that's true organizers
like the daughters of temperance push
for laws to limit or ban alcohol finally
utopian communities popped up around the
country groups like the Shakers and
Brook Farm tried to create perfect
societies by rejecting traditional norms
and focusing on communal living but if
there's one thing this course should
teach you it is that life is suffering
and of course all of these communities
fail in this time period
African-Americans both enslaved and free
faced enormous challenges but they also
created communities and strategies to
protect their dignity and Fight For
Freedom so what stayed the same and what
changed in the South enslaved people
continued to resist their oppression but
their efforts to end slavery were
largely limited to rebellions and most
were unsuccessful one of the most famous
was Nat Turner's rebellion in 1831
Turner an enslaved preacher led a
violent Uprising in Virginia that
resulted in the deaths of over 50 people
the Rebellion terrified Southern whites
and led to harsher slave laws meanwhile
in the north abolitionist movements were
growing the free African-American
population increased especially in
cities like Philadelphia and Boston many
African-Americans founded their own
communities and institutions to preserve
their culture and fight for their rights
for example the African Meeting House in
Boston built in 1806 became a hub for
Education abolitionist meetings and
religious services one key thing
African-Americans did was use the press
in 1827 Freedom's Journal became the
first blackowned and operated newspaper
in the United States it gave
African-Americans a platform to speak
out against slavery and challenge racist
policies but you have to understand the
biggest thing that helped these
African-Americans was their own
spiritual commitment like for example
enslaved people in New Orleans gathered
at Congo Square on Sundays to play music
dance and preserve their cultural
Traditions these gatherings help them
maintain a sense of identity and
Community even in the face of Oppression
so here's the line to take away from
this whole video while African-Americans
faced harsh conditions of discrimination
they found ways to resist and fight for
their freedom America a beautiful
country of Glorious cities but there's
really only one place you can call
perfect that's right the American South
so what was the South like in this time
period well first off geography and the
environment shaped the South's economy
and identity southern land was perfect
for growing cash crops like cotton
tobacco and sugar but there was also a
problem over cultivation the soil in the
Southeast became depleted so slave
holders moved West explaning plantations
into new fertile lands in places like
Alabama Mississippi and Texas all right
enough beating around the bush so
slavery although most Southerners didn't
own enslaved people the Region's economy
and Leadership were built on slavery
Southern leaders like John C Cod went
from calling slavery a necessary evil to
defending it as a positive good
according to Cal hod slavery wasn't just
acceptable it was essential to the
southern way of life this focus on
agriculture and slavery gave the South a
distinct Regional identity while the
north industrialized and Diversified the
South stayed Locked In traditional
agriculture Staples and resisted change
Southern Business Leaders kept relying
on Cotton exports to drive their economy
which made the South heavily dependent
on both slavery and foreign trade so
what to take away from this is the South
became its kind of own place and culture
during this time period and this tension
with the north would wait say it with me
cause a future War thank you so much for
watching also why do you can click on
this end screen here it's a
non-educational video I spent a lot of
time
on come on man
please please